<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True relation vvithout all exception, of strange and admirable accidents which lately happened in the kingdome of the Great Magor, or, Magull, who is the greatest monarch of the East Indies : as also vvith a true report of the manners of the countrey, of the commodities there found, with the like of sundry other countreyes and ilands, in the East Indies / written and certified by persons of good import, who were eye-witnesses of what is here reported.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22105171</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22105171</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25062</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25062)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1734:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True relation vvithout all exception, of strange and admirable accidents which lately happened in the kingdome of the Great Magor, or, Magull, who is the greatest monarch of the East Indies : as also vvith a true report of the manners of the countrey, of the commodities there found, with the like of sundry other countreyes and ilands, in the East Indies / written and certified by persons of good import, who were eye-witnesses of what is here reported.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.D. for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East Indies --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Mogul Empire.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25062:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION VVITHOUT ALL EXCEPTION, OF Strange and Admirable Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, which lately
happened <hi>in the Kingdome of the great</hi> MAGOR, or MAGVLL, who is the greateſt Monarch of
the <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS ALSO</hi> VVith a true Report of the Manners of <hi>the Countrey; of the Commodities
there found,</hi> With the like of ſundry other <hi>Countreyes and Ilands, in the</hi> EAST
INDIES.</p>
            <p>Written and certified by perſons of good import, who were eye-witneſſes of what is here
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at
his Shop in <hi>Popes</hi>-head <hi>Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:25062:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25062:2"/>
            <head>Late and admirable Newes, from the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> and the Countrey of the great
<hi>Magor,</hi> teſtified by perſons of great import, as ſhall appeare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeare of our Lord 1618. and in the moneth of Iune, we arrived at the Cape of <hi>Good
hope,</hi> where we found the people of the Countrey, albeit Heathen and Idolaters, yet very kind
and friendly vnto vs, for ſome ſmall quantitie of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and old Copper, we had of them vpon
exchange Beeues and Mutton. This Cape (otherwiſe called the Cape of <hi>Bona Speranſa</hi>) is
very temperate, and agreeth well with the conſtitution of our people. Foure or fiue hundred
perſons, ſicke of the ſcurvie, and other diſeaſes of the Sea, they all recovered their
health perfectly within a very few dayes.</p>
            <p>They haue a very pleaſant drinke, which they call <hi>Toddye,</hi> like in taſte to white
Wine, which diſtelleth from the Pahneto trees. At our departure from this Cape we ſayled two or
three dayes in a Sea like in collour to whey, whoſe bottome could not ſound.</p>
            <p>We came afterwards to the Countrey of the great <hi>Magor,</hi> or as ſome call him
<hi>Magull,</hi> his Laſcar, which is his Traine, which followeth and alwayes goeth with him in
his progreſſes, conſiſteth vſually of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25062:3"/>200000. people of all ſorts. Theſe lodge all in fayre Tents, richly hanged,
which being pitched accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order of that Countrey, they make a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gorgeous and
glorious ſhow, as of a moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and large Cittie.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Magor,</hi> hath a place called the <hi>Maoll,</hi> in which he keepeth a thouſand
women to ſerue his luſtfull deſires.</p>
            <p>When he maketh his progreſſe, his Concubines goe with him in all ſumptuous maner, carried
vpon Elephants in Caſtles, richly covered, or vppon mens ſhoulders, in a frame made like the
vpper part of a Coach, but not ſo cloſe covered. He hath vnder him 37. Provinces, and very many
goodly Citties: the length of his Countrey is 2800 myles: the breadth 1900 myles.</p>
            <p>When he admitteth to his preſence the Perſian Embaſſador, or the Embaſſador of any
other migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie King, when he giueth them either louing or kind ſpeeches, or lookes, then the
Embaſſadors in token of thankfulneſſe, kiſſe the earth. But Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> the
King of Great <hi>Brittaynes</hi> Embaſſador would not ſo much derogate from his place, to
abaſe himſelfe ſo demiſſiuely. Notwithſtanding, he was alwayes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with more
and greater reſpects then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Embaſſador.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Magor,</hi> doth euery yeere weigh himſelfe in a Ballance made for the purpoſe;
firſt, he weigheth himſelfe with waights of Siluer, next he weigheth himſelfe with waights of
Gold, and laſtly, with Iewels, and precious ſtones: his waight of ſiluer, and gold, he giueth
away liberally at his pleaſure, after
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25062:3"/>he is weighed, he mounteth into his Throne, and then he throweth amongſt the
ſtanders by, a great quantitie of Siluer and Gold, made hollow, like to the forme of Nutmeggs,
and ſuch other Spices, which his Countrey doth afford. Theſe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies being ended, then he
beginneth to Carowſe and largely to drinke with his Nobles, till they be all drunke. The Scales
with which he is weighed, are all of maſſie Gold, richly beſet with precious ſtones.</p>
            <p>No man hath any Land in this <hi>Magors</hi> Countrey but himſelfe, he giueth pentions and
taketh away pentions at his pleaſure. No child inherits any thing which his Father had in
poſſeſſion, but at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Magor:</hi> all Honor and Gentilitie dyeth with
the perſon who had any, and returnes backe to the <hi>Magor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſheweth himſelfe in publike and open maner to the people, at the leaſt, three times in
a day; firſt, at the Sunne-riſing, to which he maketh low Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Secondly, at noone, at
which time he ſeeth Elephants fight, or ſome other paſtimes prouided for him. Thirdly, before
the Sunne ſet, but when the Sunne is ſetting he deſcendeth from his Throne, and ſheweth as
low obey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſance as he did at the riſing.</p>
            <p>At all theſe times, whoſoeuer commeth vnto him as a Sutor, vſeth no other meanes for his
diſpatch, but to hold vp a paper in his hand, and he is heard immediately, and encountreth the
beſt fortune which Sutors can deſire, for either he preſently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth his Sute, or hath a
preſent deniall; there are no maſters of Requeſts, nor any delatory references vpon any
petition.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25062:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Magors</hi> people are gouerned by no other lawes but what lie in his breaſt, and the
breaſts of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, yet there is no place where buſineſſes are ſooner
diſpatched, or where Iuſtice is more vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnpartially miniſtred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curſero,</hi> the eldeſt Sonne of <hi>Magor,</hi> being of an haughtie and aſpiring
Spirit, practiſed to take from his Father both Crowne and kingdome, but <hi>Magor</hi> not onely
tooke his ſonne priſoner, but with him ſome 2000. of his chiefeſt followers, having taken
his ſonne, he placed him to ſee the execution of thoſe two thouſand he had taken. The
manner of the execution being terrible, for they were put into the ground vpon ſharpe ſtakes,
and ſo left to dye. After this execution, <hi>Magor</hi> ſhut vp and ſealed his ſonnes
eyes, ſo that for three yeares he ſaw no light of Sunne or Moone at all: ſeaven yeares he
kept him in cloſe Priſon, but at this time he hath a little more liberty. This Prince is of a
different diſpoſition from his Father, for he keepeth but one wife, and is a great fauourer and
protector of Chriſtians; he is generally beloued of all men. <hi>Magor</hi> will not vndertake,
nor do any buſineſſe of import, but as he ſhall be directed and counſailed by his
Aſtrologers, and Magitians, when they tell him the day and houre are fortunate then hee
adventureth vpon any thing, hee cannot endure to heare any talke or mention made of Death which is
the moſt deſperate and greateſt follie which our age can or doth afford, nay what
madneſſe is it? not to heare talke, nor make proviſion for that which cannot bee avoyded. God
hath pointed nothing more certaine then Death, becauſe wee ſhould ever
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25062:4"/>conſider of it; and nothing more vncertaine, then the houre of Death; becauſe
every houre we ſhould be provided for it. <hi>Magor</hi> being much delighted, with
Aſtrologers, Magitians, and Witches, of which his Country is repleniſhed, there came vpon a
time one of that Crue vnto him, and preſented vnto him an Ape; telling <hi>Magor,</hi> that the
Ape could doe ſtrange and admirable <hi>Tricks:</hi> well quoth <hi>Magor</hi> we will make
tryall of your Apes skill, and cunning, &amp; thereupon commanded the Ape and her Maſter to be
carried out of that roome, into another that they might not ſee what was done, in their abſence
<hi>Magor</hi> tooke a Ring from his finger, &amp; hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes about him a great number of
Boyes, ſome 200. or thereabouts, <hi>which hee keepeth for vnnaturall and beaſtly vſes,</hi>
he gaue the Ring to one of the Boyes and bad him hide it, then theſe Boyes flocking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
the Ape and his Maſter were called for: now quoth <hi>Magor</hi> let your Ape trie her skill, I
haue loſt my Ring, let vs ſee if ſhee can finde it; the Apes Maſter commanded the Ape to
fetch the Ring, the Ape went immedidately to the Boy which had the Ring and tooke it out of his
boſome and brought it to <hi>Magor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who wondring much at it, he cauſed the ſecond time the Ape and her maſter to retire out of
ſight, and in their abſence, hee cauſed his Secretary to write in ſeverall papers, the
Names of ſome twelue or fourteene, of the greateſt Gods, and Prophets which either were heard
or knowne to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, either in his Countrey or in any place of the World, which being
written, they were mingled
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25062:5"/>on an heape and layd vpon a table, Then the Ape was called for, and commanded to
take the Name of the greateſt God &amp; trueſt Prophet from amongſt thoſe papers, the Ape
went preſently to the Papers, and turning them vp, from amongſt them all, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tooke out the
Name of Ieſus and delivered it to <hi>Magor,</hi> wherupon <hi>Magor</hi> and the reſt of his
Nobles, were much amazed: but vppon ſecret conference amongſt themſelues, they reſolved to
make further tryall: whereupon the Maſter and the Ape were commaunded to goe to a further roome,
and ſome perſons commanded to watch them, that the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of all deceiueable courſes
might be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and cleered: the papers were written againe with the ſame Names, and more
were added, which being done; the Ape was called for the ſecond time, and to make choyce as
formerly ſhee had bin directed, ſhee preſently went to the papers and made the ſame choyce,
which before ſhee had done: which ſtroke <hi>Magor</hi> and his Nobles in a greater a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze then
at the firſt: notwithſtanding a third tryall was made, but with the like &amp; ſame
ſucceſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a great Noble man humbly beſought <hi>Magor</hi> that hee might make
the fourth tryall, which was graunted him, this great man was called <hi>Mattolet Chan,</hi> which
in their Language ſignifieth (the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Lord) Hee cauſed the Names to be written the fourth
time, and mingled together, and caſt in a heape vpon the Table, the Ape was called as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
ſhee had beene, and commanded to make choyce of the greateſt God or Prophet, whoſe name was
conteined in thoſe papers. The Ape went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25062:5"/>to the heape, and ſlightly and ſcornefully tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them over, but tooke vp no
paper but returned to her maſter. <hi>Magor</hi> and his Nobles wondred more at this then of what
paſſed before, and asked the Apes maſter, what might be the cauſe why the Ape would not
bring any paper as before ſhee had done, but turned them vp in ſo ſcornefull a maner, perhaps
quoth the maſter, the name which the Ape looketh for, is not there amongſt them; then the
papers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined, the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> was miſſing, now quoth <hi>Magor,</hi> let
the Ape ſhew cunning to fetch that paper, wherein that name is written. The Ape receiuing her
command, made preſent haſt to <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolet Chan,</hi> and leapt vpon him, and withall thruſt
her hand into his boſome, and drew out the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> which ſhee brought
haſtily to <hi>Magor.</hi> This being ſo ſtrange an accident, was wondred at of all the
ſtanders by, whereof ſome were Iewes, ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans, ſome Chriſtians, with others.
This hath beene averred to be true, by maſter <hi>Edward Terry,</hi> Preacher to Sir <hi>Thomas
Roe,</hi> who heard it credibly reported, as aforeſaid. And Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> hath
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the ſame for truth to ſundry right honorable parſonages. Maſter <hi>Terry</hi>
the Preacher hath often ſeene the Ape.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>Magor,</hi> and generally all the <hi>Indians</hi> of his Countrey are giuen over
to fleſhly pleaſures: they may, and doe keepe as many wiues and concubines as they will, or are
able to maintaine. What miſery doe theſe <hi>Indians</hi> endure, to haue ſo many women
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, when as there be many Engliſh men are grieuouſly vexed to haue the company but of
one.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25062:6"/>But perhaps the <hi>Indian</hi> women are of a farre milder temper then the
Engliſh, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewed. The <hi>Indians</hi> are more jealous of their women
and wiues, then either Spanyards, or Italians. The Father will not truſt his ſonne, after he
commeth to twelue yeares of Age, except he be gelded. The <hi>Indian</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their houſes
are commonly covered, and if any woman goe abroad vncovered, ſhee is reputed a Whore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magors</hi> ſubiects are tall, and of comely perſonage, but of a tawnie coullor, but
they are faint hearted; <hi>Magor</hi> will vſually ſay, that one Portingall will beate three
of his ſubiects, and one Engliſh man will beate three Portingalls. In this Countrey there are
many ſeuerall Sects, ſome called <hi>Banians,</hi> who will kill nothing that hath life, no not
ſo much as ſnakes. They haue Hoſpitalls to keepe and cure lame Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, lame Doggs, lame
Birds, or any lame Creature, and when they be cured, they are ſet at libertie. The manner of that
Countrey is to burne the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the dead, and the wiues willingly burne with their husbands.
But of late the women beginne to breake that cuſtome.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> vnder <hi>Magor,</hi> worſhip euill fauoured vgly Idolls, which they
call, <hi>Pagods:</hi> their Prieſts are called <hi>Ioggis,</hi> or <hi>Bramines;</hi> their
Church they call <hi>Muskitts;</hi> they goe on Pilgrimage to ſeuerall places; Some to
<hi>Mecha</hi> in Arabia; Some to the Head of the Riuer <hi>Ianges,</hi> wherein they throw
ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and gold, according to their abilities, and after waſh themſelues in the River, and
then they thinke they are pure and cleane from all ſinne.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:25062:6"/>
            <p>Theſe people haue many feaſts, and many faſts, which they keepe with ſundry idle
Ceremonies, ſome of them mourne in blew, others as <hi>Iapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> mourne in white. They are
skilfull in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, eſpecially, in Simples.</p>
            <p>The learning which they haue, which is but ſmall, is in the Mathematicks, and in Naturall
Phyloſophy; they haue ſmall ſtore of Bookes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no Printing amongſt them;
all their Bookes are Manuſcripts.</p>
            <p>Their vulgar ſpeech is called <hi>Induſtan.</hi> The ſpeech at <hi>Magors</hi> Court, is
vſually the Perſian Language. Their learned tongue is the Arabian; the common people are very
apt to immitate any thing which they ſee to be done by Strangers.</p>
            <p>I cannot let paſſe a ſtrange and wonderfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which fell out in <hi>Magors</hi>
Court, and hath beene by Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> reported confidently for Truth. There was a
<hi>Raſa,</hi> (ſo great Princes are called,) who was an abſolute Atheiſt, who would
alwayes ſcornefully, and diſdainefully ſpeake and diſpute againſt the Deitie, not
enduring eyther himſelfe, or any other, where hee might oppoſe to acknowledge any God-head.
This great Prince ſporting himſelfe among his Concubines, one of them who was moſt fauoured
of the Prince, and might bee moſt bold with him, when hee was flouting, and ieſting againſt
the Deitie, pluckt from his breaſt an hayre, and withall a droppe of blood followed, which was
not regarded at all at the firſt; This very place within very fewe dayes beganne to feſter, and
by degrees
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25062:7"/>grew to that extremitie, that the paine was intolle-rable, and withall prouing
to be a Gangrene; having vſed all the meanes, which Phyſicke, or Surgery might afford him, it
proued irrecoverable. This <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> ſeeing his eſtate, and that he had no hope of life,
but a dreadfull expectation of imminent death, ſent to <hi>Magor</hi> to take his leaue of him,
<hi>Magor</hi> ſent divers of his Nobles vnto him, to comfort him, with all the beſt offers and
ſpeeches which any ſubiect might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire from ſo mightie a Monarch. Which when the Nobles
had delivered vnto him, he made anſwere in this manner; My Lord <hi>Magor,</hi> is a great
Monarch to command vpon earth, but there is a more omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Monarch, which hath abſolute
command and power in Heauen and Earth. You all know, I was an oppoſer, an enemy, a contemner of
all Deitie, and againſt that omnipotent Maieſtie of Heauen. He hath now ſhewed and
manifeſted his power and Iuſtice vpon me, who now lye in torment, euery minute of an houre
expecting to die. What I would not acknowledge in my life, I am conſtrained to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and
confeſſe vpon my death, for wee which liue at randome, and ſpeake at large in our liues, when
death worketh natures diſſolution, wee are then compelled to change our former opinions, and to
acknowledge our former errors. I was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, by my owne experience I dare and can aſſure
you, what is one of the greateſt cauſes of Atheiſme; wicked liues doe wiſh, there were no
God to puniſh their offences after this life, and therefore doe flatter themſelues in their
life; they frame to themſelues all the reaſons they can deuiſe, to perſwade themſelues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25062:7"/>there is no God. But my Lords, there is no Atheiſt which dare at the houre of
his death maintaine and defend that Doctrine of Atheiſme, which he did in life, for nature it
ſelfe doth conſtraine them to a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble recantatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the houre of death, as you may now
behold a grieuous example in me: what would not I giue? what would not I do? my Lords if I might
haue longer time of life to acknowledge &amp; confeſſe free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainely that God head,
which formerly I haue with ſcorne and malice ſo wickedly denied: who would haue imagined that I
being a Souldier ſhould not rather haue died vpon ſome honorable wound, given by ſword or
launce; then ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to die vpon the plucking of one hayre from my breaſt, this kind
of death, as it is moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me, ſo it doth more manifeſt, and illuſtrate the
Divine power to bee moſt Omnipotent and miraculous. My Lords, my vitall powers doe faile mee, I
can ſpeake no more, onely this for a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, which I pray you deliver alſo to my great
Soveraigne <hi>Magor,</hi> doe you all flie and take heede of Atheiſme, ſeeke out with all the
care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence you can, thou knowledge of the onely true and Omnipotent God, dare not liue
thoſe wicked liues, nor maintaine thoſe horrible opinions whileſt you are in health, which as
you ſee moſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in me are ſo terrible and horrible at this houre of my death;
having ended theſe words, this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince dyed.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Magors</hi> Countrey wee ſayled towardes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ilands, and arrived at an Iland
called <hi>Zeloon,</hi> which Iland yeeldeth Cinnamon, and other ſpices
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25062:8"/>in great aboundance, it yeeldeth alſo Pearles, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, Saphires, Garnets, and
ſundry other pretious ſtones.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Zeloon</hi> wee arrived at an Iland called <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matra,</hi> which yeeldeth Pepper,
Gold, Beniamin, Camphire, with ſundry other Rich Commodities, afterwards we ſayled to
<hi>Patanie,</hi> an Iland governed by a Mayden Queene.</p>
            <p>From this wee arrived at <hi>Iapan,</hi> which is one of the greateſt and goodlieſt Ilands
of the World, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving great ſtore of Gold Mines, and of Silver, they haue Silver, of three
ſorts all vnſtamped, they haue ſmall plate, which goeth in the market for buying of
victuales: they haue other peeces of plate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamped, more finer Silver, and that goeth in the
Country, to buy all other commodities; they haue a third ſort of plate, finer ſilver then any
Spaniſh money, and this is carried away by Strangers.</p>
            <p>This Countrey is Governed by an Emperour, who hath vnder him 62. Kings, the Revenews of this
Emperour are infinite, a great part raiſed by Rice, the People of this Countrey are proud and
haughty, very warlike, yet exceeding obedient to their Emperour, and the Kings, to whom they are
Subiects. They are very kinde to Strangers: Iuſtice, in this country is ſevere without
partialitie; Theeues are not impriſoned but preſently executed, If a murther be committed, and
the murtherer eſcape, hee who apprehendeth him, hath 300. pounds gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him vpon the deliverie of
the murtherer; ſo that fewe or none of the murtherers eſcape preſent exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: In this
Countrey a man may walke without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25062:8"/>danger all houres of the night, ſo he doe not miſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaue himſelfe. If
any controverſie ariſe betwixt partie and partie, it is foorthwith decided, their Lawes are
<hi>Leges talionis,</hi> Eye for Eye, Tooth for Tooth, Hand for Hand, and Life for life, they
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp and pray all to a Saint, called <hi>Ameda,</hi> whom they eſteeme to bee a Mediator
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and them; when a Souldier dieth, they are perſwaded hee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth preſently to
<hi>Ottango Fatech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the God of Warre.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25062:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25062:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
